{
  "reference_number": "11720",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions (including from new forest planting) and using some emissions reductions from overseas (international carbon units) that have strong environmental safeguards",
      "answer_index": 2,
      "notes": "Climate change is a global problem so the solutions for NZ can legitimately be found through partnerships with other countries rather\n than going it alone which could be more difficult and more economically risky."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "But ONLY to make it even stronger, i.e. a greater reduction than net zero by 2050."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": "But of course the 2050 target cannot be reduced from net zero emissions, only improved, as stated in question 4."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "But exceptional circumstances would only be: in the event of a natural disaster or major human-made disaster eg. nuclear accident,\n war."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The overall reduction by 2050 and the proportion of that required in the budget period to stay on track - using results of completed\n\nbudget periods and the already fixed budget in periods coming up. The details of the reduction and hence the allowed quantity of\nemissions relating to every industry etc sector and appointed lead officials within each sector that the Government will have to work\n\nwith. Consultation with ENGOs and other non-commercial stakeholders. And others - this is not a complete list!"
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Mechanisms would be required for spreading fairly the cost of admin and compliance across all businesses involved in each service,\n\netc. and government."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I'm excited to be submitting on the Zero Carbon Bill as I am a long-time conservationist, environmentalist and supporter of Green\n\nparties, in Australia as well as New Zealand. My submission therefore entirely supports the introduction of this bill. Congratulations to\nthe coalition government for this and all the fantastic changes you are making in New Zealand. New Zealand may be a small country,\n\nwith a small population and a small proportion of the world's greenhouse gas emissions but it is respected internationally, and other\nnations will be inspired by our actions to tackle climate change - it is great to lead the way, and the certainty that this bill will give to\n\nindustry will drive a new clean, efficient economy, that will finally show the world how we can live sustainably on this planet, to provide\ninter-generational equity, which just makes sense - no more greed! The Commission needs to include experts on the natural world\nand it's protection for its own sake, accounting for the environmental services that it provides ($ value). This would also encompass\n\nhow we can help nature (species, ecosystems, etc.) adapt to climate change. The Commission's expert on agriculture would need to\npropose examination of sheep and dairy farming and the conversion of such land to forest growing for carbon sequestration,\n\nincluding government sponsorship for conversion. This is probably too specific for this submission but regarding transport in, out of\nand around NZ, of people and goods - alternatives to air transport, such as modern large sailing craft or the use of biofuels must be\n\ninvestigated. I believe that The Zero Carbon Act should also provide a framework for the help we give our neighbouring countries\n(principally the Pasifika region) facing climate change including transparency in international climate finance. For our Pasifika\n\nneighbours, NZ must support them with their specific problems and the actions to fix them whether financial, on-the-ground work or\ntechnology for adaptation or halting climate change, or assistance in creating appropriate legislation or strategies/planning. Yours\nfaithfully, Derek G. Walker."
    }
  ]
}
